Roberto S. Silva Filho, Ph.D.

home: San Francisco Bay Area, Dublin, CA, USA mobile: (949) 885-6821

e-mail: Roberto.SilvaFilho@gmail.com

http://www.ics.uci.edu/~rsilvafi

#### **EXPERTISE**

Experienced software engineering researcher and practitioner in the fields of software automation tools and collaborative applications using Web technologies, IoT, AI, mobile and wearable computing. Developing apps to optimize industrial work by connecting people, insights and machines. Research contributions to: automated and collaborative software engineering, software architecture, model-driven systems development & testing, event-driven middleware, workflow management systems and groupware.

## **EDUCATION**

2009. Ph.D. Information and Computer Sciences. UC, Irvine, CA, USA. GPA: 3.974/4.0

Concentration areas: Empirical Software Engineering, Extensible Event-Based Middleware, CSCW

Dissertation Title: An Empirical Study of Publish/Subscribe Middleware Versatility

2003. M.Sc. in Information and Computer Sciences. UC, Irvine, CA, USA. GPA: 3.906/4.0

Concentration area: Software Engineering

2000. **M.Sc.** in Computer Science. University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Brazil, GPA: 3.857/4.0 *Thesis Title*: Distributed Software Architectures for Large-scale Workflow using CORBA

1998. B.Sc. in Computer Engineering. University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Brazil, GPA: 0.748/1.0

### **EMPLOYMENT**

2013 - present. GE Global Research, San Ramon, CA

Lead Scientist, Human Systems Interaction Lab, AI and Learning Systems Research Group.

*Areas*: Full stack R&D of industrial intelligent software systems. Applying UX, IoT, AI services & Software Engineering techniques to empower industrial workers with insights, automating and optimizing their workflow. Development of web-based, mobile & wearable computing apps, distributed simulation platforms and UX concept prototypes. Production of patents & research papers.

### 2009 – 2013. SIEMENS Corporate Technology, Princeton, NJ

Software Engineering Researcher, Software Architecture Development Lab.

*Areas*: Research and development of advanced software engineering tools & methods for the automation and optimization of industrial problems. Software Architecture Analysis and Improvement, Software Quality Assurance, Model-Driven Development & Testing, Workflow Automation. Production of patents & research papers.

Summer 2004. **IBM T. J. Watson Research Center (Collaborative User Experience Group),** Cambridge, MA **Research Intern:** Developed, benchmarked and compared different architectural approaches for the construction of contextual collaboration servers used within IBM products.

Technologies: Java, RMI, contextual collaboration servers, performance simulation and benchmarking.

2000 – 2009. University of California, Irvine, CA

(2002-2009): Graduate Research Assistant

(2000-2002): Teaching Assistant

# SELECTED PROJECTS

2014 – present. GE Global Research.

**Automation and optimization of industrial work.** Research & development of mobile and wearable apps used to optimize and automate industrial workflows. Helping people connect to insights & capture data as they perform industrial work. Interfacing with industrial machines and robots using IoT protocols including Bluetooth, MQTT, and ROS. Integration with corporate information systems via JDBC and REST endpoints. Selected projects:

- MATERIA: collaborative data analysis & sharing. Web app based on knowledge graphs that allows material science engineers to analyze and share experimental results. Developed IDE & microservices for: SemTK (<a href="http://semtk.research.ge.com">http://semtk.research.ge.com</a>) an open-source semantic toolkit developed at GE Research.
- Voice RCL. Speech-controlled locomotive concept for GE Transportation. Mobile app integrated with desktop train simulator that demonstrate use of speech for command and control of locomotives.

- **Distributed Platform for Rapid Simulation Prototyping**. Design & implementation of message-driven framework supporting micro-services to facilitate the development of next generation train handling and control center for GE Transportation. Implemented Web and mobile apps using the new framework.
- Machining Cost Optimization. Developed Web app that optimizes CNC machining operations, allowing aviation workshop workers to save costs, and share their expertise throughout the organization.
- Smart Outage (Field Vision): Mobile app used by GE Power engineering teams as a single point of access to all their needs including: project management, time keeping, schematics & documents, reporting, and collaboration. Implemented server-side integration middleware and offline operation.
- Model-based robotic inspection. Implemented UI-Controls bridge allowing semi-autonomous robotic inspections of industrial assets.
- Wearables@GE. Apply speech recognition and wearable computing in support of different hands-free industrial scenarios involving field workers: wireless measurements, photo documentation, real-time video.

### 2009 – 2013. SIEMENS Corporate Research.

**Software Tools for test automation and software quality analysis**: Project manager & developer for Tedeso/UML, a model-based testing IDE with novel features and capabilities including requirements-driven regression and prioritization of tests. Tedeso can achieve high degrees of test coverage, by automatically generating tests based on UML system specification, at a fraction of time of conventional manual testing approaches. *Main Role*: Product developer & manager of a small team of interns working on Tedeso/UML IDE. *Technology stack:* Java, Eclipse RCP, GEF, UML, model-based testing, Jenkins, Cruise Control.

- 2007 2009. UC, Irvine (UCI). **Analysis of Flexibility Trade-offs in Publish/Subscribe Infrastructures**: Developed a versatile pub/sub middleware evaluating it against different research and industrial publish/subscribe infrastructures, measuring and comparing their performance, maintainability, reusability, usability and flexibility. Produced different versatile software design principles and best practices. *Technologies*: Java and RMI, CORBA-NS, JMS, JavaSpaces, Siena, YANCEES, OO metrics and analysis.
- 1998 2000. University of Campinas, São Paulo, Brazil (UNICAMP): Agent-based Workflow on Distributed Environment: Developed and evaluated the scalability of a distributed architecture for large-scale workflow as part of my Master's Thesis. This work shows the scalability benefits of a peer-to-peer agent-based workflow management system and discusses extra security and management costs induced by the approach.
  Technology stack: Java, JavaCC, CORBA, Workflow Management Systems, Mobile Agents, benchmarking.

### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Fall 2001 – Spring 2002. Introduction to Computer Science II. UC, Irvine (UCI)
 Topics: Data Structures, Software Complexity, Java and Scheme programming.

 Fall. 2000. Introduction to Software Engineering. UC, Irvine (UCI)
 Topics: Software Engineering fundamental principles, techniques and processes.

### HONORS AND AWARDS

2007. Bren School Summer Dissertation Fellowship, UC, Irvine, CA.
2001. **Best thesis award** (second place): VIII CLEI-UNESCO Latin American M.Sc. Thesis Context.
1998 – 2000. Scholarships to support M.Sc. Studies from FAPESP and CNPq, Brazil Research Agencies.

## **SKILLS**

Programming Languages: Java, JavaScript, C#, Python, Go, LISP, Pascal, SQL, Prolog, C, C++, others.
 Technologies: UI frameworks: AngularJS, Polymer, React; Mobile computing: Android, Cordova; Distributed Systems: REST Web Services, Docker, Event-based middleware, Distributed Network Objects (RMI, CORBA); Software Engineering: Software Product Line Engineering, UML Modeling, Software Architecture and ADLs, Aspect-Oriented Programming, Database and Internet Programming. Others: XML, Eclipse RCP and OSGi.
 Processes: Agile Methods and Object-Oriented design principles and metrics, Rational Unified Process.
 Operating Systems: Unix/Linux and Windows administration.

#### PATENTS & PUBLICATIONS

Author of more than 35 peer-reviewed publications; 6 patents and 12 technical reports. More details at the website: https://rsilvafi.github.io/publications.html